XIAOJIAN XU

[Homepage] [Google Scholar] [Github] [Twitter] [Linkedin]

Department of Computer Science and Engineering & Washington University in St. Louis

About me

Current research

My current research pursues to combine computational imaging, optimization, and machine learning to
enable new intelligent imaging technology for various imaging applications including denoising, deblurring,
super-resolution, image segmentation, optical microscopy, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), radar, and autonomous driving, etc. My research efforts are taking place at two complementary levels: (a) the fundamental
and mathematical aspects of imaging; (b) application-oriented projects in collaboration with researchers in
medicine, biology, and computer vision.

Research interests

Computational Imaging, Optimization, Deep Learning, Inverse Problems, Computer Vision, Signal Processing

EDUCATION

Washington University in St. Louis (WUSTL), St. Louis, MO, USA 9/2017-6/2022 (expected)

Ph.D student in Computer Science (GPA: 3.87/4.00), advised by Dr. Ulugbek Kamilov

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC), Chengdu, China 9/2014-6/2017

M.Eng in Communication & Information Engineering (Graduated with Honors)

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC), Chengdu, China 9/2010-6/2014

• B.Eng in Communication Engineering (GPA: 3.89/4.00)

Working Experience

Facebook Reality Labs Research (FRLR)

5/2021-8/2021

Research intern with Dr. Brian Wheelwright

Seattle (remote)

• Built the ray-tracing model for peripheral display system in Oculus, solved its display calibration problem, and designed an efficient camera-to-display mapping for its real-time rendering using neural representation.

Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories (MERL)

5/2019-8/2019

Research intern with Dr. Hassan Mansour

Boston

 Investigated in 3D tomographic imaging problems and solved the problem by proposing two distinct methods, model-based optimization and data driven deep learning.

AWARDS & HONORS

Honors	
 Honored Ph.D student in Computer Science & Engineering department 	2021
Outstanding Graduate Student	2017
Scholarship	
Graduate Student First-Rank Academic Scholarship	2016
Graduate Student Second-Rank Academic Scholarship	2015
Graduate Student First-Rank Academic Scholarship	2014
National Inspirational Scholarship	2013
People's First-Rank Scholarship	2012
National Inspirational Scholarship	2011
Others	
• Third-prize of 'Internet+' Entrepreneurship Competition in Sichuan Province	2016

Great Award of Intelligent City Technology Competition

2016

Award of Hackathon Programming Competition

2015 2011

Second Prize of Electronic Design Competition in UESTC

SKILLS

- Languages: Python, Matlab, C, Java
- Skills: Optimization, Inverse problems, Tensorflow, Pytorch, Deep learning, Linux, TCP/IP

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Model-based deep learning for imaging and vision

8/2020 - Present

• Developed imaging-model-assisted learning methods such as unsupervised learning, self-supervised and unrolling framework for different imaging tasks with various noise corruption challenges ([1, 2, 6, 7, 9]).

Learning-based optimization for imaging and vision

8/2020 - Present

Extensively investigated in variants of Plug-and-Play priors (PnP) and Regularized by denoising (RED) approaches for various imaging tasks by combining the imaging models with the deep-learning priors, in both theory and practice ([3, 4, 5]).

Compressed and stochastic algorithms for large-scale imaging

7/2018 - Present

• Investigated in large-scale imaging problems by developing stochastic variants of optimization- and learning-based algorithms with convergence guarantee ([6, 7, 10]).

Some earlier research experience

3/2014 - 6/2017

- Intelligent home system design and development.
- Routing and resource scheduling algorithms for large-scale network software defined networks (SDN).

Publications

Preprints

- [1] **X. Xu** et al., "Learning-based Motion Artifact Removal Networks (LEARN) for Quantitative R_2^* Mapping," arXiv:2109.01622 [eess], Sep. 2021, [Online]. Available: http://arxiv.org/abs/2109.01622
- [2] S. Kahali, S. V. V. N. Kothapalli, **X. Xu**, U. S. Kamilov, and D. A. Yablonskiy, "Deep-Learning-Based Accelerated and Noise-Suppressed Estimation (DANSE) of quantitative Gradient Recalled Echo (qGRE) MRI metrics associated with Human Brain Neuronal Structure and Hemodynamic Properties," bioRxiv, 2021, doi: 10.1101/2021.09.10.459810.

Published

(* indicates equal contribution)

- [3] X. Xu, Y. Sun, J. Liu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Provable convergence of plug-and-play priors with MMSE denoisers," IEEE Signal Process. Lett., vol. 27, pp. 1280–1284, 2020.
- [4] X. Xu, J. Liu, Y. Sun, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Boosting the performance of plug-and-play priors via denoiser scaling," in 54th Asilomar Conf. on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 2020, pp. 1305–1312.
- [5] X. Xu*, Y. Sun*, Z. Wu*, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Scalable Plug-and-Play ADMM With Convergence Guarantees," IEEE Trans. on Comp. Imag., vol. 7, pp. 849–863, 2021.
- [6] J. Liu, Y. Sun, W. Gan, X. Xu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "SGD-Net: Efficient Model-Based Deep Learning With Theoretical Guarantees," IEEE Trans. on Comp. Imag., vol. 7, pp. 598–610, 2021.
- [7] J. Liu, Y. Sun, W. Gan, X. Xu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Stochastic Deep Unfolding for Imaging Inverse Problems," in IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), 2021, pp. 1395–1399.
- [8] X. Xu, O. Dhifallah, H. Mansour, P. T. Boufounos, and P. V. Orlik, "Robust 3D Tomographic Imaging of the lonospheric Electron Density," in 2020 IEEE Int. Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS), 2020, pp. 437–440.

[9] J. Liu, Y. Sun, X. Xu, and U. S. Kamilov, "Image restoration using total variation regularized deep image prior," in 2019 IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), 2019, pp. 7715–7719.

[10] X. Xu and U. S. Kamilov, "SignProx: One-bit proximal algorithm for nonconvex stochastic optimization," in IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), Brighton, UK, May 2019, pp. 7800–7804.

INVITED TALKS

- SIAM Conference on Imaging Science, 07/2020
- UCLouvain, Image and Signal Processing Group Seminar, 09/2020
- Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 10/2021

PROFESSIONAL SERVICES

- Conferences reviewer: ISBI, ICASSP
- Journals reviewer: IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP), IEEE Transactions on Computational Imaging (TCI), Optics Communications, Scientific Reports

TEACHING & SUPERVISION EXPERIENCE

(Head) TA for Optimization

2019-2020

Assistant Instructor

St. Louis

 Head assistant instructor and guest lecturer for course "Optimization" and "Large-Scale Optimization for Data Science"

Students supervision

7/2018-Present

Research Supervisor

St. Louis

Current students

- Eddie Chandler, "Inhomogeneity correction for MRI", now B.S. student at WUSTL
- Yixuan Luo, "Deep-learning-based image segmentation", now M.S. student at WUSTL
- Michael Kincheloe, "Reinforcement learning for MRI artifacts correction". now B.S. student at WUSTL Previous students
- * Zhixin Sun, "Neural representation for MRI reconstruction", coming Ph.D student at WUSTL
- Weijie Gan, "Fast MRI reconstruction and artifacts correction", now Ph.D student at WUSTL
- Jiarui Xing, "Deep-learning-based MRI artifacts correction", now Ph.D student at University of Virginia
- Shiqi Xu, "Sparse Fourier ptychographic microscopy", now Ph.D student at Duke University
- Hao Tang, "Adversarially robust classifiers for image reconstruction", now M.S. student at WUSTL
- Ryogo Suzuki, "Unfolding networks for image restoration", now at Rakuten Group, Inc.
- Yukun Li, "Single image denoising", now at Baidu Inc.
- Fa Long, "Dictionary learning for image restoration", now at Tencent Inc.